Guide to the American Iron Company Records 1744-1806 (bulk, 1764-1806) MS 18
New-York Historical Society
American Iron Company records
1744-1806 (bulk, 1764-1806)
New-York Historical Society
American Iron Company
MS 18
2 Linear feet (4 boxes, 1 volume)
The collection contains documents pertaining to the establishment and dissolution of American Iron Company in New York and New Jersey, including deeds for the purchase and sale of land, articles of agreement, bills from vendors, letters demanding payment of overdue accounts, paid checks, minutes of Trustees' meetings, and the company's ledger and checkbook.
Access Restrictions
Materials in this collection may be stored offsite. For more information on making arrangements to consult them, please visit www.nyhistory.org/library/visit.
Arrangement
This collection is organized in four series:
Series I. Correspondence 1764-1806, undated
Series II. Legal documents, 1751, 1765-1806, undated
Series III. Corporate documents, 1788-1800, undated
Series IV. Financial documents, 1766-1802, 1806, undated
Historical Note
The American Iron Company, established in London in 1767, was the reorganization of an iron-manufacturing venture (1764-1767) whose original backers went bankrupt. The trustees for the new enterprise were originally Major General David Greeme; George Jackson, Deputy of Admiralty; Commodore Arthur Forrest; Richard Willis; and Richard Atkinson. Peter Hasenclever was named the agent for the Company and managed the Company's Ringwood (purchased by American Iron Company in 1764), Long Pond (founded by Hasenclever in 1766), and Charlotteburgh iron manufacturing companies in New Jersey and New York, in which he had interests. He served as agent from June to October, 1767. Financial problems related to the bankruptcy of his former partners Andrew Seton and Charles Crofts resulted in his return to London in 1768.
The Company's iron works were subsequently managed by Seton Humfray, Thomas Jordan, John Jacob Faesch (beginning in 1769), and Robert Erskine (d. 1780). The bankruptcy of Peter Hasenclever in 1769 weakened the Company because of his close financial relationship with it. Hasenclever's creditors therefore sought to put an attachment on the Company for their claims.
Hasenclever returned to Silesia (Germany) in 1773. The Revolution halted all legal action underway and from 1773 to 1788, the claims made against the Company were ignored. However, the iron works continued to supply material for the Revolutionary forces during this period. In 1788 Chief Justice Richard Morris of New York appointed three trustees for the Company: Peter Goelet, a New York merchant; Robert Morris, a New Jersey judge; and William Popham, a New York attorney. Their responsibility was to ensure that all of the Company's outstanding debts were settled, and in pursuance of this they conducted a sale of all Company lands in 1795. By 1806, all of the Company's accounts had been settled.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Donation, 1991.
Scope and Contents
The collection contains predominantly copies of legal documents pertaining to the establishment and dissolution of American Iron Company in New York and New Jersey, including deeds for the purchase and sale of land, articles of agreement, bills from vendors, letters demanding payment of overdue accounts, paid checks, minutes of Trustees' meetings, and the company's ledger and checkbook. A bill dated 1744 possesses no apparent relation to the bulk of the records. A document of 1751 is relevant but is chronologically isolated from the bulk of the records (1764-1806).
The records richly illustrate standard legal processes in England and the Colonies immediately before and after the Revolution. Documents relevant to the land sale of 1795 also show surveying and business practices of post-Revolutionary New York. The collection's early documents (1767-1773) show some of the problems that arose due to the distance between the trustees in London and the iron works in New York and New Jersey. Documents in the later period (1788-1806), including checks and bills, create a portrait of a bankruptcy and liquidation of assets in this period.
Accounts.; Bills (financial); Checkbooks; Checks (bank checks); Claims; Correspondence.; Ledgers (account books); Minutes (administrative records); Powers of attorney; Receipts (financial records); Iron mines and mining -- New Jersey.; Iron mines and mining -- New York (State).; Merchant companies -- New York (N.Y.).; Passaic County (N.J.); Ringwood (N.J.); Westchester County (N.Y.); Atkinson, Richard, active 1770; Bond, Phineas; Debrosses, Elias; DeLancey, John; Denise, Nicholas; De Witt, Simeon, 1756-1834; Duryee, Abraham; Edwards, Edward; Erskine, Robert, 1735-1780; Forrest, Arthur; Goelet, Peter; Goelet, Peter P.; Greeme, David; Greg & Cunningham; Hamilton, Alexander, 1757-1804; Hardenbrook, John A.; Harison, Richard; Hasenclever, Peter, 1719-1793; Hoffman, Nicholas; Ingraham, Nicholas; Jackson, George; Judah, Benjamin; Judah, Samuel; Lydig, David; McKenney, John; Morris, Robert, approximately 1745-1815; Petry, William; Popham, William; Ridland, John; Shay, Patrick; Stahl, Dietrich; Troup, Robert, 1757-1804; Virginia Company of London; Vrooman, Lawrence; Willis, Richard; Wolff, John; Zabriskie, John
- Series I. Correspondence, 1764-1806, undated
  - Correspondence, 1764-1776 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence, 1784-1793 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence, 1794 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence, 1795 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Correspondence, 1796-1798 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Correspondence, 1799 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Correspondence, 1800-1806, undated (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Correspondence, Reade & Yates, 1768 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Correspondence, Reade & Yates, 1769 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Correspondence, Reade & Yates, 1770 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Correspondence, Reade & Yates, 1771 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Correspondence, Reade & Yates, 1772-1773 (Box 1, Folder 12)
- Series II. Legal documents, 1751, 1765-1806, undated
  - Legal documents, 1751, 1765 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Legal documents, 1766-1767 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Legal documents: articles of agreement, 1767 May 11 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Legal documents, 1769-1789 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Legal documents: deed to J.A. Hardenbrook, 1788 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Legal documents, 1790-1795 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Legal documents, 1796-1806, undated (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Legal documents: Claims and demands, 1767-1769 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Legal documents: Claims and demands (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Legal documents: Land surveys, 1769-1799 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Legal documents: Affidavits, 1769-1798, undated (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Legal documents: Rulings, 1771-1799 (Box 2, Folder 12)
- Series III: Corporate documents, 1788-1800, undated
  - Corporate documents: Rough minutes, 1788-1794 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Corporate documents: Rough minutes, 1795-1800, undated (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Corporate documents: Memoranda, 1786-1799, undated (Box 3, Folder 3)
- Series IV. Financial documents, 1766-1806, undated
  - Financial documents: Accounts, 1766-1769 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Financial documents: Accounts, 1770-1778 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Financial documents: Accounts, 1785-1794 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Financial documents: Accounts, 1795-1806 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Financial documents: Ledger, 1789-1794 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Financial documents: Waste[e] book, 1789-1793 (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Financial documents: Receipts, 1776-1795 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Financial documents: Receipts, 1796-1801 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Financial documents: Bills, 1744-1789 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Financial documents: Bills, 1794-1804 (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Financial documents: Bills of exchange, 1767-1769 (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Financial documents: Checks, 1775-1806 (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Financial documents: Checkbook, 1800-1806 (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - Financial documents: Calculations, Undated (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - Reade & Yates's Accounts with the American Company of London, 1769-1773 (Volume 1)